Jessica C. Garwood

Dept. of Marine and Coastal Sciences,
Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey
71 Dudley Road
New Brunswick, NJ 08901

Website
JessCG.github.io
jgarwood@marine.rutgers.edu
English, French (fluent)
Italian (conversational)

Research Interests

My research interests focus on elucidating the fundamental dynamics that govern small-scale physical-biological interactions in the coastal ocean. By combining *in situ* measurements with numerical models and theory, I seek to interpret the ocean as it relates to plankton. At the core of my research is a desire to develop and employ underwater robotic plankton swarms to capture these dynamics.

Education

2019 PhD Oceanography - Scripps Institution of Oceanography, UCSD Transport in internal waves with a background flow: Lessons learned from robotic larval mimics Advisors: Peter J. S. Franks & Andrew J. Lucas

2014 MSc Oceanography - Dalhousie University

Seasonal variation and biological effects on mudflat erodibility in the Minas Basin, Bay of Fundy

Advisor: Paul S. Hill

2011 BSc Marine Biology & Oceanography, First Class Honours - Dalhousie University

Appointments

2020 -	Postdoctoral Associate, Dept. of Marine and Coastal Sciences, Rutgers University	
	Linking behavior and transport of larvae using waves and turbulence as cues	
	Principal investigators: Heidi Fuchs, Greg Gerbi, Bob Chant	
2013-2019	Graduate Student Researcher, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, UCSD	
2017	Teaching Assistant, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, UCSD	
2011-2013	Graduate Student Researcher, Dept. of Oceanography, Dalhousie University	
2011-2012	Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Oceanography, Dalhousie University	
2009-2011	Undergraduate Student Researcher, Dept. of Oceanography, Dalhousie University	

Peer-Reviewed Publications

McCormick, L.R., S. Gangrade, **J.C. Garwood**, N.W. Oesch, and L.A. Levin. Defining a visual luminoxyscape to describe oxygen and irradiance constraints on larval habitat in a changing ocean. *Submitted to Limnol. Oceanogr. Lett.*

Garwood, J.C., A.J. Lucas, P. Naughton, P.L.D. Roberts, J.S. Jaffe, L. deGelleke, and P.J.S. Franks. 2021. Larval cross-shore transport estimated from internal waves with a background flow: The effects of larval vertical position and depth regulation. Limnol. Oceanogr. 66(3):678-693. doi:10.1002/lno.11632

Garwood, J.C., R.C. Musgrave, and A.J. Lucas. 2020. Life in Internal Waves. Oceanography. 33(3): 38-49. doi:10.5670/oceanog.2020.313

Garwood, J.C., A.J. Lucas, P. Naughton, M.H. Alford, P.L.D. Roberts, J.S. Jaffe, L. deGelleke, and P.J.S. Franks. 2020. A novel cross-shore transport mechanism revealed by subsurface, robotic larval mimics: Internal wave deformation of the background velocity field. Limnol. Oceanogr. 65(7):1456-1470. doi:10.1002/lno.11400

Franks, P.J.S., **J.C. Garwood**, M. Ouimet, J. Cortes, R. Musgrave, and A.J. Lucas. 2020. Stokes drift of plankton in linear internal waves: Cross-shore transport of neutrally buoyant and depth-keeping organisms. Limnol. Oceanogr. 65(6):1286-1296. doi:10.1002/lno.11389

Garwood, J.C., P.S. Hill, H.L. MacIntyre, and B.A. Law. 2015. Grain sizes retained by diatom biofilms during erosion on tidal flats linked to bed sediment texture. Cont. Shelf Res. 104:37-44. doi:10.1016/j.csr.2015.05.004

Garwood, J.C., P.S. Hill, and B.A. Law. 2013. Biofilms and size sorting of fine sediment during erosion in intertidal sands. Estuar. Coasts. 36:1024-1036. doi:10.1007/s12237-013-9618-z

In-Preparation Publications

Garwood, J.C., H.L. Fuchs, G.P. Gerbi, E.J. Hunter, and R.J. Chant. Estuarine larval retention enhanced by tuning into turbulence and tuning out waves. *In preparation*.

Moulton, M., S.H. Suanda, **J.C. Garwood**, N. Kumar, M.R. Fewings, J.M. Pringle. 2023. Mechanisms for the transport of nutrients, plankton, and pollutants across the nearshore region. Ann. Rev. Mar. Sci. *In preparation*.

Grants & Fellowships

2014-2016	Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship - PhD
2013-2014	Regents Fellowship
2011-2012	Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship - MSc
2007-2011	Chancellor's Scholarship
2007-2011	Provincial Millennium Excellence Award
2011	NSERC Undergraduate Student Research Award
2010	NSERC Undergraduate Student Research Award
2009	NSERC Undergraduate Student Research Award
2007-2008	Residence Scholarship
2004-2006	Full scholarship - United World College of the Adriatic

Honors

2015 Fager Award - recognizes excellence in quantitative training of peers

2014 Canada Governor General's Academic Medal - Gold

2007-2011 Dean's list

2011 Hugh P. Bell Scholarship2011 J. G. Ogden Memorial Prize

2011 Vemco Scholarship

2010 David Durward Memorial Prize

2009 Shao Hua and Wen Hsiang Yoh Prize in Biology

2004 Canada Governor General's Academic Medal - Bronze

Presentations

Invited

- **2021** Gordon Research Conference speaker invitation. Session: Novel approaches to observing in coastal systems. Postponed to 2023. *Coastal Ocean Dynamics Gordon Research Conference*.
- **2021** Estuarine and nearshore larval retention enhanced by sinking in turbulence and depth-keeping in internal waves. March 2021. *Department of Marine Sciences, University of Connecticut.*
- **2020** Cross-shore transport in internal waves: Lessons learned from robotic larval mimics. Nov. 2020. *Department of Oceanography, Dalhousie University.*
- **2020** Cross-shore transport in internal waves: Lessons learned from robotic larval mimics. Oct. 2020. *Applied Ocean Physics and Engineering, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution.*
- **2020** Transport in coastal internal waves: Lessons learned from robotic larval mimics. Jan. 2020. *Department of Marine and Coastal Sciences, Rutgers University*.

Oral presentations

- **2020 Garwood, J.C.**, A.J. Lucas, P. Naughton, M.H. Alford, P.L.D. Roberts, J.S. Jaffe, L. deGelleke, and P.J.S. Franks. Three-way interaction between larval swimming behavior, internal waves, and the mean flow enhances cross-shore transport. Feb. 2020. *Ocean Sciences Meeting, San Diego, CA, USA*.
- **2018 Garwood, J.C.**, P.J.S. Franks, P. Naughton, P.L.D. Roberts, A.J. Lucas, J.S. Jaffe. A ratchet to shore: How background flow and nonlinear internal waves can interact to enhance transport of quasi-Lagrangian plankton mimics. Sept. 2018. *Eastern Pacific Ocean Conference, Mount Hood, OR, USA*.
- **2018 Garwood, J.C.**, P.J.S. Franks, P. Naughton, P.L.D. Roberts, A.J. Lucas, J.S. Jaffe. A ratchet to shore: transport of quasi-Lagrangian plankton mimics by nonlinear internal waves. Feb. 2018. *Ocean Sciences Meeting, Portland, OR, USA*.
- **2017 Garwood, J.C.**, P.J.S. Franks, P. Naughton, P.L.D. Roberts, A.J. Lucas, J.S. Jaffe. A ratchet to shore: transport of quasi-Lagrangian plankton mimics by nonlinear internal waves. Sept. 2017. *Scripps Student Symposium, San Diego, CA, USA*.

- **2016** Law, B.A., T.G. Milligan, P.S. Hill, **J.C. Garwood**, V. Zions. Temporal and spatial changes in grain size on a macro-tidal channel-flat complex: Results from Kingsport, Nova Scotia, Bay of Fundy. Feb. 2016. *Ocean Sciences Meeting, New Orleans, LA, USA*.
- **2013** Law, B.A., P.S. Hill, T.G. Milligan, P.L. Wiberg, **J.C. Garwood**, V. Zions. Temporal and spatial change in grain size and erodibility on a macro-tidal channel-flat complex in Kingsport, N.S., Canada, versus a mesa-tidal channel-flat complex in Willapa Bay, Washington, USA. Nov. 2013. *Conference of the Coastal & Estuarine Research Federation, San Diego, CA, USA*.
- **2012 Garwood, J.C.**, S.S. Kienast, and P.S. Hill. Evidence of dust deposition in a core from the Eastern Equatorial Pacific on glacial-interglacial timescales. Dec. 2012. *AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA, USA.*
- **2012 Garwood, J.C.**, S.S. Kienast, and P.S. Hill. Evidence of dust deposition in a core from the Eastern Equatorial Pacific on glacial-interglacial timescales. March 2012. *Conference of Dalhousie Oceanography Graduate Students, Halifax, NS, Canada.*
- **2012 Garwood, J.C.**, P.S. Hill, and B.A. Law. Biofilms and size sorting of intertidal sediment during erosion. Feb. 2012. *Ocean Sciences Meeting, Salt Lake City, UT, USA*.
- **2011 Garwood, J.C.**, and P.S. Hill. Effects of biofilms on sediment sortability. March 2011. *Conference of Dalhousie Oceanography Graduate Students, Halifax, NS, Canada.*

Poster presentations

- **2016 Garwood, J.C.**, R.C. Musgrave, R.C., P.J.S. Franks. Modeling plankton aggregation and transport by nonlinear internal waves propagating onshore. Feb. 2016. *Ocean Sciences Meeting, New Orleans, LA, USA*.
- **2016** Jaffe, J.S., B. Laxton, **J.C. Garwood**, P.J.S. Franks, P.L. Roberts. A micro-fluidic treadmill for observing suspended plankton in the lab. Feb. 2016. *Ocean Sciences Meeting, New Orleans, LA, USA*.
- **2014 Garwood, J.C.**, K. Devitt, R. Cox, and P.S. Hill. Comparison of biofilm effects on sediment erosion at two intertidal sites with distinct surface sediment grain size. Feb. 2014. *Ocean Sciences Meeting, Honolulu, HI, USA*.
- **2013 Garwood, J.C.**, and P.S. Hill. Seasonal and biofilm effects on sediment erosion and sorting in an intertidal mudflat in the Bay of Fundy, Canada. Nov. 2013. *Conference of the Coastal & Estuarine Research Federation, San Diego, CA, USA*.
- **2013 Garwood, J.C.**, P.S. Hill, and B.A. Law. Mudflat biofilms coarsen suspended sediment in the Minas Basin. May 2013. *Nova Scotia Tidal Energy Research Symposium and Forum, Acadia University, Wolfville, NS, Canada.*
- **2011 Garwood, J.C.**, and P.S. Hill. Effects of biofilms on sediment sortability. Feb. 2011. *Cameron Conference, Halifax, NS, Canada*.

Student mentorship

2020 Samikshya Poudel

RIOS undergraduate summer intern, Rutgers

Samikshya investigated the likelihood of larvae spawned near Cape Hatteras to be transported North and back to the shelfbreak via the Gulf Stream. Analyses were conducted using virtual larval tracks generated with ROMSPath and ROMS output. My role was to supervise the project.

2018 Shailja Gangrade

Scripps Undergraduate Research Fellow

Shailja compiled CTD data to map ocean depths with optimal light and oxygen levels based on larval visual system requirements. My role was to provide programming mentorship, and co-advise with Lillian McCormick, under the supervision of Lisa Levin and Peter Franks.

2012 - 2013 Rachel Cox

Dalhousie Undergraduate Honours Research Project

Rachel investigated the effects of benthic fauna on sediment resuspension on an intertidal flat in the Bay of Fundy. I helped frame her research project, and provided input on the experimental design and data interpretation. Advisor: Paul S. Hill.

2011 - 2012 Karen Devitt

Dalhousie Undergraduate Honours Research Project

Karen investigated sediment retention by benthic biofilms grown in the lab. I helped frame her research project, and provided input on the experimental design. Advisor: Paul S. Hill.

Teaching

Co-instructor

2015 SIO 278: Introduction to R for Oceanographers - SIO

Guest lecturer

2021 11:628:410: Biophysical interactions: from barnacles to jellyfish - Rutgers University
2020 11:628:410: Biophysical interactions: from barnacles to jellyfish - Rutgers University

2018 SIO 90: Perspectives on Ocean Sciences - SIO2017 SIO 285: Physical-Biological Interactions - SIO

Teaching assistant

2017 SIO 134: Introduction to Biological Oceanography - SIO

Instructor: Mike Landry

2012 OCEA 3004: The Last Billion Years - Dalhousie University

Instructor: Paul S. Hill

2011 OCEA 2002: The Blue Planet - Dalhousie University

Instructor: Paul S. Hill

Field work

Deployment of robotic swarm & moorings, small boat operations

2016 Principal investigator, PhD research - 2 weeks, Mission Beach, CA, USA

Research cruises

2018	Introduction to at-sea sampling for summer interns, R/V Robert Gordon Sproul - 1 day,
	San Diego, CA, USA
2017	Night shift leader, SCoNE student cruise, Inner-Shelf Dynamics Experiment, R/V Robert
	Gordon Sproul - 10 days, Point Sal, CA, USA
2016	Chief scientist, class project, R/V Robert Gordon Sproul - 3 cruises totaling 5 days, San
	Diego, CA, USA
2013	Class cruises, R/V Robert Gordon Sproul - 2 cruises totaling 2 days, San Diego, CA, USA
2013	Research assistant, S0-228, R/V Sonne - 25 days, Jayapura, Indonesia to Townsville,
	Australia

Sediment collection on intertidal flats

2011-2012	Principal investigator, MSc research - twice monthly for 8 months, Bay of Fundy, NS,
	Canada
2010	Principal investigator, BSc research - twice monthly in summer, Cole Harbour, NS, Canada
2010	Research assistant - 3 weeks, Willapa Bay, WA, USA

Service

2020	Moderator & organizer, Panel on Diversity in STEM and screening of $Picture\ a\ Scientist$ - Rutgers University
2017-2019	Diversity Advisory Committee - SIO
2018	Session co-chair - Eastern Pacific Ocean Conference, Sept. 2018, Mount Hood, OR, USA Session: Interdisciplinary studies examining transport and mixing from the shelf to the shoreline.
2017	Discussion leader, Munk Centennial Symposium on Internal waves, turbulence, and the overturning circulation of the ocean, May 2017, San Diego, CA, USA
2017	Organizer, Scripps Student Symposium - SIO
2014-2015	Organizer, Ecology Seminars - SIO
2011-2012	Organizer, Oceanography Seminars - Dalhousie University
2011-2012	Student recruitment volunteer, Oceanography - Dalhousie University
2011-2012	Treasurer, Dalhousie Oceanography Student Association
2012	Organizer, Conference of Dalhousie Oceanography Graduate Students

Outreach

2020 Scientific adviser, United World Challenge

Designed coding activities introducing ocean concepts, and participated in a podcast

(Episode 9) available on Spotify, Apple Podcasts, and others.

2016 - 2018 Outreach, Ocean Discovery Institute

Developed two year-long research projects for low income, middle school students

Manuscript reviews

2020	Coral Reefs (1)
2020	Frontiers in Marine Science (1)
2020	Journal of Marine Research (1)
2020	Marine Ecology Progress Series (1)
2019-2020	Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science (2)

Broader community experience

2014-2019	Climbing gym instructor, Outback Climbing Center, UCSD
2016-2018	Volunteer shift leader, Banff Centre Mountain Film and Book Festival, Banff, Canada
2014-2015	Volunteer, Banff Centre Mountain Film and Book Festival, Banff, Canada
2006-2007	Volunteer recreation program coordinator, Fort Good Hope, Northwest Territories, Canada